Employee Ownership Project; Records apap120
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Employee Ownership Project Records
1967-2000
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Employee Ownership Project
apap120
10.17 cubic ft.
Records of independent, non-profit organization which promotes the creation and growth of micro-enterprises and small business ventures to improve the lives of low and moderate income residents of the Capital Region.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Librares, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Richard L. Shirey in September 2001.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains board meeting minutes, charter financial records, executive director subject files, and loan case files.
Access
Access to Series 6 is restricted. No client name, client business name, telephone number, address or personal data can be made public for at least 50 years (2051 A.D.). Data may be aggregated for research purposes. Access to all other records is unrestricted.
Administrative History
The Employee Ownership Project (EOP) is an independent, non-profit organization formed in 1987, whose main objective is to improve the lives of low and moderate income residents of the Capital Region through the creation and growth of micro-enterprises and small business ventures. The EOP supports and promotes the creation and development of enterprises which feature democratic ownership and decision making structures. EOP has reached out to and engaged Albany’s Arbor Hill and West Hill neighborhoods in order to establish the organization’s presence in working and low income communities. EOP has offered a series of workshops and seminars on starting businesses and enterprises as well as reaching out to adolescents.
The EOP has been influential in starting dozens of small businesses, which have created or maintained over one hundred jobs for low and moderate income individuals. The EOP helped start up businesses such as a convenience store, a sewing factory, a dry cleaning business, a contracting firm, and an asbestos and hazardous waste removal business. The EOP serves people who might not otherwise be considered entrepreneurs and tries to match people with complimentary skills necessary in effort to create successful businesses.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged into six series and the series are arranged alphabetically.
Series 1 - Administration, 1987-2000, 1 cubic ft.
Series 2 - Organizational Contacts, 1987-1998, 1 cubic ft.
Series 3 - Network Strategies, 1981-1997, 1 cubic ft.
Series 4 - Community Outreach, 1970-2000, .83 cubic ft.
Series 5 - Albany County Opportunity Inc., 1967-1973, .17 cubic ft.
Series 6 - Loan Case Files, 1984-1997, undated, 6.17 cubic ft.
Social Activists and Public Advocates; Labor; Albany, New York; Employee ownership--United States; Albany Pine Bush Preserve (Albany, N.Y.); Albany (Or.). Planning and Zoning Commission; Fundraising--New York (State)--Albany (N.Y.); Albany (N.Y.); Meetings; Fundraising; Cooperative; Center; Minutes; Neighborhoods; ICA; Community; Personnel; Employee Ownership Project
- Administration, 1987-2000; Undated; 1
  - About EOP, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 1)
  - Chart of Accounts, 1983 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 2)
  - Board Minutes, 1987-1988 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 3)
  - Board of Directors, 1988-1992 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 4)
  - Board Minutes, 1989 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 5)
  - Board Minutes, 1990 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 6)
  - Board Minutes, 1991 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 7)
  - Board Minutes, 1992 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 8)
  - Board Minutes, 1993 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 9)
  - Board Meetings, 1993 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 10)
  - Board Meetings, 1994 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 11)
  - Board Meeting Notes, 1994 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 12)
  - Board Minutes, 1994 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 13)
  - Board Meetings, 1995 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 14)
  - Board Minutes, 1995 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 15)
  - Board Meetings, 1996 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 16)
  - Board Minutes, 1996 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 17)
  - Board Minutes, 1997 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 18)
  - Board Meetings, 1998 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 19)
  - Board Minutes, 1998 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 20)
  - Board Nominations and Job Descriptions, 1996-1997 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 21)
  - Board Planning, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 22)
  - Board Surveys, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 23)
  - By-laws and Mission, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 24)
  - Capitol District Community Economic Development Network, 1993 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 25)
  - Catholic Charities Wire Transfers, 1993 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 26)
  - Certificate of Incorporation, 1987 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 27)
  - Community Development Black Grant Proposal, 1997 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 28)
  - Community Economic Development Mondragon Model, 1990; 1994; 1997 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 29)
  - Corporate Records Kit, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, 1989; 2000 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 31)
  - Development Committee, 1996 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 32)
  - Development Finance Study, 1992 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 33)
  - Diocesan Development Project Proposal, 1990 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 34)
  - Executive Committee, 1997 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 35)
  - Frederick McDonald Trust Grant Sienna College, 1997 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 36)
  - Human Resources Committee, 1996 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 37)
  - Internal Affairs Nomination Committee, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 38)
  - Long Range Planning Committee, 1992 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 39)
  - McTAP Training, 1998 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 40)
  - Mailing Lists, 1993 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 41)
  - Personnel Directors Search Advertising, 1988 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 42)
  - Personnel Funding From Catholic Charities, 1988-1992 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 43)
  - Personnel Policies, 1987; 1995-1997 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 44)
  - Powers, Joseph, Obituary, 1994 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 45)
  - Program Committee, 1996 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 46)
  - Recruitment Outreach Committee, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 47)
  - Social Dimension of Workers Cooperatives, 1996 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 48)
  - Staff Meetings, 1995-1997 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 49)
  - Tax Exempt Certificate, 1987-1989; 1997 (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 50)
  - Youth Entrepreneur Program, Undated (Box 1 (1-Administration), Folder 51)
- Organizational Contacts, 1987-1998; Undated; 2
  - Articles and News Clippings, 1988-1993 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 1)
  - Babson College, 1993-1995 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 2)
  - Bank Symposium, 1996-1997 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 3)
  - Ben and Jerry's, 1990 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 4)
  - Bloom, Jane, 1991-1992 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 5)
  - Business Maintenance Organization, 1989-1992 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 6)
  - Chase Chemical, 1996 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 7)
  - Charitable Venture Foundation, 1995 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 8)
  - Citibank Proposal, 1989 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 9)
  - Corpus Christi Church, 1996 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 10)
  - Department of Economic Development Recycling Grant, 1990 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 11)
  - Department of Labor Microenterprise, 1994 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 12)
  - The Discount Foundation, 1997 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 13)
  - Donation Response, 1993-1994 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 14)
  - Empowerment Zones, 1996 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 15)
  - Enterprise Community, 1995-1998 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 16)
  - Fee Scale, Undated (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 17)
  - Fleet Bank, 1994-1997 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 18)
  - Fleet Youths Grant, 1997 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 19)
  - Ford Foundation, 1994-1995 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 20)
  - Fundraising, 1989-1992 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 21)
  - Fundraising Letter, 1997 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 22)
  - Gift In Kind America, 1992-1996 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 23)
  - Hitachi Foundation, 1997 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 24)
  - Howard and Bush, 1997 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 25)
  - Industrial Cooperative Association, 1987-1993 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 26)
  - Jobs Now, 1996 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 27)
  - Kazanjan Economics Foundation Inc., 1991 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 28)
  - Kellogg Foundation, 1996 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 29)
  - Leviticus Alternative Fund, 1987-1997 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 30)
  - Marketing Course, Undated (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 31)
  - Marketing Plans, 1991 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 32)
  - McDonald Trust, Siena College, 1997 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 33)
  - Merck Foundation, 1993-1996 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 34)
  - Miscellaneous Grants, 1992-1997 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 35)
  - Miscellaneous Grants, 1994-1997 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 36)
  - Mohawk Hudson Community Foundation, 1990-1996 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 37)
  - Mott Foundation, 1997 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 38)
  - Ms. Foundation, 1995-1996 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 39)
  - Needmor Fund, 1990 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 40)
  - New Business Ventures and Entrepreneurship, 1992 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 41)
  - New York State Legislature, 1997 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 42)
  - Possible Grants, 1995-1996 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 43)
  - Reaching the Hip Hop Generation, 1990 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 44)
  - SEFA Campaign, 1993 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 45)
  - Siena College, 1988-1989; 1995; 1997 (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 46)
  - St. Madeleine Sophie Sacrificial Sharing, Undated (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 47)
  - Loan Papers, Undated (Box 1 (2-Organizational Contacts), Folder 48)
- Network Strategies, 1981-1997; Undated; 3
  - Business Incubator Without Walls, 1997 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 1)
  - Capitol District Community Economic Development Network Meetings, 1993-1994 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 2)
  - Capitol Region Education Center for Economic Development, 1987-1992 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 3)
  - Capozolla, Nick, 1992-1995 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 4)
  - Davis, Bonita, 1992 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 5)
  - Demographics, Undated (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 6)
  - Dudley Park Residents Council, 1993 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 7)
  - EOP Goal and Mission, 1989 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 8)
  - Federation of Industrial Retention and Renewal, 1989-1996 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 9)
  - Finn, Jonathan Vista Volunteer, 1995-1997 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 10)
  - Human Resources Committee, 1996-1997 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 11)
  - Ideas and General Information, 1991-1992 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 12)
  - Industrial Cooperative Association, 1984-1989 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 13)
  - ICA Documents, 1981-1986 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 14)
  - ICA Education Models, 1989-1990 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 15)
  - ICA General, 1983-1993 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 16)
  - ICA Getting Organized For Worker Ownership, 1987 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 17)
  - Interns, 1988-1990 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 18)
  - Job Placement Consortium, Undated (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 19)
  - Job Service Corps, 1995 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 20)
  - Long Term Planning, 1992 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 21)
  - Microenterprise Project, 1990-1996 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 23)
  - National Center for Employee Ownership, 1985-1987 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 24)
  - National Cooperative Bank, 1988-1991 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 25)
  - National Cooperative Bank, Bank Notes, 1988-1992 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 26)
  - National Equity Development Group, 1995 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 27)
  - Naigutuch Valley Project, 1985-1986 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 28)
  - The Neighborhood Works, 1993; 1997 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 29)
  - New York Center for Employee Ownership and Participation, 1986-1989 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 30)
  - Organizations, 1980-1995 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 31)
  - Rensselaer County Entrepreneurship Assistance Program, 1997 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 32)
  - Research, 1995 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 33)
  - Saint Patrick’s Parish, 1990-1992 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 34)
  - Small Business Development Center, 1990 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 35)
  - Small Business Network, 1992 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 36)
  - Staff Development, 1996 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 37)
  - Strategy, 1987-1988 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 38)
  - Tri-City Shalom Americorps, 1997 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 39)
  - Volunteerism, 1984-1986 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 40)
  - Welfare to Work, 1995 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 41)
  - Workers Owned Sewing Company, 1981-1982; 1992 (Box 1 (3-Network Strategies), Folder 42)
- Community Outreach, 1970-2000; Undated; 4
  - Advisory Council, 1989-1992; 1997 (Box 1 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 1)
  - Albany Black Investors Inc., 1970 (Box 1 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 2)
  - Albany-Colonie Regional Chamber of Commerce, 1989-1996 (Box 1 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 3)
  - Albany Community and Trust, 1992 (Box 1 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 4)
  - Annual Dinner, 1992-1994 (Box 1 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 5)
  - Conference and Training on Democratic Employee Ownership First Annual March, 1989 March 10; 1989 March 11 (Box 1 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 6)
  - Employee Stock Ownership Plan Association, 1987-1989 (Box 1 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 7)
  - Farmworkers, 1999-2000 (Box 1 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 8)
  - Finance Class, 1992-1993 (Box 1 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 9)
  - Frank Kramer Award, 1993-1994 (Box 1 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 10)
  - Fundraising Dinner, 1994 (Box 1 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 11)
  - Hill and Vale Business Loan Fund, 1997-1998 (Box 1 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 12)
  - Hill and Vale Business Loan Fund, Loan Proposal for Johnson Designs, 1997-1998 (Box 1 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 13)
  - Mailing Lists, 1993 (Box 1 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 14)
  - Microenterprise Workshop Senses, 1991; 1995-1997 (Box 2 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 1)
  - Neighborhood Community Centre, 1992-1996 (Box 2 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 2)
  - Neighborhood Resource Center, Childcare, 1991-1992 (Box 2 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 3)
  - Neighborhood Resource Center, Finances, Undated (Box 2 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 4)
  - Neighborhood Resource Center, Kuumba Arts and Cultural Center, 1993 (Box 2 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 5)
  - Neighborhood Resource Center, Maintenance, 1995 (Box 2 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 6)
  - Neighborhood Resource Center, Meetings, 1992-1997 (Box 2 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 7)
  - Neighborhood Resource Center, Police, 1995 (Box 2 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 8)
  - Neighborhood Resource Center, Rental Agreements, 1994-1995 (Box 2 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 9)
  - Newsletters and Flyers, 1993 (Box 2 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 10)
  - Open House Materials, 1988 (Box 2 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 11)
  - Outreach, 1988-1994 (Box 2 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 12)
  - Outreach Arbor Hill, 1990-1991 (Box 2 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 13)
  - Outreach Banks, 1996 (Box 2 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 14)
  - Outreach Businesses, 1988 (Box 2 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 15)
  - Outreach, Chambers of Commerce, 1996 (Box 3 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 1)
  - Outreach, Churches, 1991-1993 (Box 3 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 2)
  - Outreach Committee, 1997-1998 (Box 3 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 3)
  - Outreach, De Fosses, Helen, 1996 (Box 3 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 4)
  - Outreach, Education, 1988 (Box 3 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 5)
  - Outreach, Immigrant Workers, 1994 (Box 3 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 6)
  - Outreach, Labor, 1988-1990 (Box 3 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 7)
  - Outreach, Saratoga, 1991 (Box 3 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 8)
  - Outreach, Schenectady, Undated (Box 3 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 9)
  - Outreach, Siena College, 1988; 1992; 1996 (Box 3 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 10)
  - Outreach, Siena College, Building Networks Conference, 1995 (Box 3 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 11)
  - Outreach, South Bronx Franklin Men’s Shelter, 1990 (Box 3 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 12)
  - Public Relations, EOP Owners Manual, 1996-1997 (Box 3 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 13)
  - Welfare Warriors, 1993-1994 (Box 3 (4-Community Outreach), Folder 14)
- Albany County Opportunity Inc., 1967-1973; Undated; 5
  - Board of Directors, 1967-1973 (Box 1 (5-Albany County Opportunity Inc.), Folder 1)
  - By-laws, Tentative and Approved, 1966 (Box 1 (5-Albany County Opportunity Inc.), Folder 2)
  - Consumer Credit Union Proposal, 1965-1968 (Box 1 (5-Albany County Opportunity Inc.), Folder 3)
  - Council of Community Services of the Albany Area Inc., 1967 (Box 1 (5-Albany County Opportunity Inc.), Folder 4)
  - Year Round Head Start, 1968 (Box 1 (5-Albany County Opportunity Inc.), Folder 5)
- Loan Case Files [RESTRICTED], 1984-1997; Undated; 6
  Scope and Contents
  Access to Series 6 is restricted. No client name, client business name, telephone number, address or personal data can be made public for at least 50 years (2051 A.D.). Data may be aggregated for research purposes. Consult a staff member for further information.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access Restricted until 2051.
  - House Rental Informational Pamphlets [RESTRICTED], Undated (Box 4 (6-Loan Case Files [RESTRICTED]), Folder 10-12)